So today is דף י', Daf Yud, we start in the middle
of ט' עמוד ב' Tes Amud Bet at the,
where are we?
תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan we're on the top.
תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan we're where?
Thank you.
So yeah, not in the middle. Near the top of ט' עמוד
ב' Tes Amud Bet about 10 lines down. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
Okay, so we're talking about again women who are מסולקת דמים, Mesulakat
Damim, who are not usually expecting to get their period. So if
they, when they find out that they've bled, they're not concerned about
that it might have happened before. And we're now dealing with a
woman who is at the period of being post-menopausal.
So let's take a look. תנו רבנן זקינה שעברו עליה שלשה עונות
וראתה. Tanu Rabbanan zekeina she-averu aleha shelosha onot vera'ata. So an elderly
woman, who we described what that was yesterday, somebody who's beginning to
appear old and now there went three periods, which means 90 days
without having had three עונות, onot, I should say, without having had
her period, without bleeding. וראתה, vera'ata, so at this moment now that
she went the 90 days, she's considered מסולקת דמים. Mesulakat Damim. So
she sees, דייה שעתה, dayyah sha'atah, and the הלכה halacha is is
that she's only worried from that moment on, she doesn't have to
be worried back 24 hours based on what we just said. Now
though, it's that's not the end of the story. ועוד עברו עליה
שלשה עונות וראתה. ve'od averu aleha shelosha onot vera'ata. Now there's another
90 days that passed and she sees again. Because you'll remember the
הלכה halacha is is that once a woman bleeds having been in
this state, whatever the various states are that she's מסולקת דמים, Mesulakat
Damim, then it's evidence that she is no longer מסולקת דמים Mesulakat
Damim and she actually is still bleeding. So if she had bled
a second time right afterwards, 30 days later, we would have said
24 hours. But what happened? She didn't bleed 30 days later. She
went another 90 days. So having gone another 90 days, it restored
her status as מסולקת דמים. Mesulakat Damim. Is everybody sort of with
me, right? She went 90 days at her during a period when
she was she was already older without bleeding. That proved that she
was post-menopausal, she was מסולקת דמים. Mesulakat Damim. She bled once. That
would have been counter-evidence and that would have said, ah, now we
see she's not מסולקת דמים. Mesulakat Damim. If she bleeds again, 24
hours back. But what happened was she didn't bleed again right away
within 30 days or within whatever. She bled again 90 days later.
So having waited the 90 days again was again a proof that
she was once more מסולקת דמים. Mesulakat Damim. So once again when
she bleeds, it again is the הלכה halacha of דייה שעתה. dayyah
sha'atah.
The same thing happens a third time. And then now she has
a new עונה onah for everything.
Very good. ועוד עברו עליה שלשה עונות. ve'od averu aleha shelosha onot.
Now she went another 90 days. Now you would say oh another
90 days it starts again, now it's also דייה שעתה dayyah sha'atah
she once again is מסולקת דמים. Mesulakat Damim. וראתה, vera'ata, no, Michael
guessed it. הרי היא ככל הנשים. harei hi ke-chol ha-nashim.
Now she is not מסולקת דמים, Mesulakat Damim, why? Because now she's
established a pattern. What's her pattern? 90 days. She bleeds every 90
days. So now she is considered to not be מסולקת דמים, Mesulakat
Damim, she's just a woman with a very long pattern. ומטמאה מעת
לעת ומפקידה לפקידה, umetimei me-et le-et umi-pekida li-fekida, and she
and she's concerned backwards 24 hours or since the last time she
checked. I mean my understanding is when women are getting to become
post-menopausal their cycles are all out of whack and sometimes it the
changes whatever I don't know if it goes as much as 90
days but anyway. But that would have established her pattern.
Okay. ולא שכיבנה אלא אפילו פחסה והותירה. velo she-kivna ela afilu pichsa
ve-hotira. And now it goes on to says ולא שכיבנה velo she-kivna
and again there's a question about how the גמרא Gemara will analyze
this in a minute. Not that she was exact, 90 days, 90
days, 90 days, or not only that she was exact but even
if she was inexact, even if once it was 90 days, once
92 days, 94 days. Totally kind of, right? Right, so you you
waited
you know either way.
Okay so let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara is going
to analyze why that would matter. So let's look at what the
גמרא Gemara says. אפילו פחסה ולא מיבעיא כיבנה. afilu pichsa ve-lo mibaya
kivna. What, you're saying even if she was inexact then we would
start being concerned but it goes without saying that if she was
exact? אדרבה, adarabba, לאו שמע מינה lav shema mina it makes sense.
כי כיבנה קבעה לה וסת ודייה שעתה. ki kivna kavla lah veshet
vedayyah sha'atah. If she's it's a different הלכה. halacha. If she is
it's you know you're making it sound like if it was exact
it's obvious we start worrying 24 hours. But if she varies maybe
it's not so obvious. הגמרא hagemara says the opposite is true. If
she's exact what did our first משנה mishna say? Our first משנה
mishna said that a woman that has an exact period who has
a וסת קבוע, veshet kavua, if she bleeds during when she's expecting
her period then she isn't concerned backwards, she's only concerned because she
expects that it will happen when she has her expected period. So
this ברייתא braita said this woman that went 90 days, 90 days,
90 days, now she has to worry 24 hours back. Oh, and
not only in the case of exact, even inexact. What do you
mean not only in the case of exact? When it's exact she
doesn't have to worry back because then she has a regular וסת,
veshet, a regular cycle. And she's not concerned backwards 24 hours. So
the גמרא Gemara says אדרבה כי כיבנה קבעה לה וסת ודייה שעתה,
adarabba ki kivna kavla lah veshet vedayyah sha'atah, if she's exact 90
days 90 days then she doesn't have to worry then she has
a regular וסת, veshet, a regular cycle and she's not concerned backwards
24 hours. וכי תימא רבנן היא דפליגי עליה דרבי דוסא דאמר אשה
שיש לה וסת מטמאה מעת לעת ve-chi teima Rabbanan hi de-paligi alei
de-Rabbi Dosa de-amar isha she-yesh lah veshet metamei me-et le-et even if
you say it's the rabbis who argue on Rabbi Dosa and say
that even a woman with a. fixed cycle when she bleeds even
on her expected period is concerned 24 hours, fine. The הלכה halachah
*halacha* might be that that woman is concerned but still, being exact
is is still less of a חידוש chiddush. *chidush* that it's still
meaning it's still it's still more of a חידוש *chidush* that you're
חושש choshesh *choshesh* when you're exact than when you're inexact. איפכא מיבעיא
*Ipcha mibaiya*, it should have said the opposite, למימר *lemaimar*, לא שפחתה
והותירה *lo shepichsa vehosira*, not only is she concerned when she's inexact
backwards 24 hours, אלא Ela, אפילו קיבנה *ela afilu kivna*, even if
it's exact, 90 days, 90 days, 90 days, where there's a reason
to say she wouldn't be concerned, nevertheless she still is. So the
language of the ברייתא Braisa *braita* is wrong. The ברייתא braisa *braita*
should have said not only is she concerned 24 hours back when
she's inexact, she should even be concerned when she's exact, or she
shouldn't be concerned when she's exact, but it's not the way we
have it phrased, which takes it that it's more obvious she's concerned
when she is exact than when she's inexact. Says the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*, says fine, switch it, תני *tani*, change the language, לא שפחתה
והותירה אלא Ella, אפילו קיבנה *lo shepichsa vehosira ela afilu kivna*. Fine,
switch the language, have it say not only when she's inexact, even
when she's exact. So the הלכה Halacha *halacha* is still the same,
whether exact or inexact she's concerned 24 hours, but we're just clearer
that it is that there's less of a reason to say that
when she's exact, when she's exact you would say maybe we don't
have to be concerned backwards, she bled when she was expected to
bleed, and nevertheless even when she's exact, which is the rabbis that
argue in רבי Rebbi דוסא *Rabbi Dosa*, we're concerned backwards 24 hours.
ואיבעית אימא הכי קאמר *Ve'iba'it eima hachi ka'amar*, if you want here's
how you can say
it, לא שקיבנה אלא שפחתה והותירה *lo shekivna ela shepichsa vehosira*, that's
actually to say like רבי Rebbi, דוסא *Rabbi Dosa*, we're not talking
about a case when she's exact, when she's exact you would not
be concerned 24 hours backwards because then we'd assume she bled when
she was expected to. אלא *Ela*, the only case is she's concerned
backwards שפחתה והותירה *shepichsa vehosira*, when it was inexact, אבל קיבנה *aval
kivna*, but if it was exact, קבעה לה וסת *kave'a la veset*,
she has an established cycle, דייה שעתה dayah sha'atah *daya sha'ata*, and
she only worries at the moment she bled, ומני רבי Rebbi דוסא
*umani Rabbi Dosa*, and this is רבי Rebbi דוסא *Rabbi Dosa*. So
fine, so this is the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, the basic point is
is that a woman goes, you know, 90 days,
she a woman when she's getting older goes 90 days, she's considered
to be מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim. *misulekes damim*, but that can be
obviously countered
by evidence, that can be changed once she starts bleeding, but another
90 days will again prove that she's back into that state. And
then it gets into this interesting idea that if she goes 90
days, 90 days, 90 days, you know, we don't say that she
keeps on returning to that state, if it happens three times that
establishes a pattern. Now by the way I should say that although
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* makes it sound like when it's exact it's
a bigger חידוש *chidush* to say she's חושש *choshesh*, there still is
a חידוש *chidush* in the inexact case, because if this woman went
first 90 days and then 93 days and then 92 days or
whatever it is, you could say she's still מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim.
*misulekes damim*. She went 90 days again without bleeding, she doesn't have
a fixed pattern, so why should we assume that she's now, you
know, regularly seeing? Why don't we just interpret this as a מסולקת
דמים mesuleket damim *misulekes damim* again even if she doesn't, you know,
because it's not being replaced by a fixed pattern, it's being replaced
by a non-fixed pattern, 90, 93, 92 and so on. So that
seems to have been another way to read the ברייתא braisa *braita*
that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* did not adopt, but I'm just sort
of mentioning that there's a חידוש *chidush* even in that case of
inexact that we consider her now to no longer be מסולקת דמים
mesuleket damim *misulekes damim* even though it's not replaced by a fixed
pattern. Okay, so anyway that's what we have by the case about
the menopausal, post-menopausal woman, that 90 days establishes that, once she bleeds
again she goes back to the previous state, but another 90 days
can re-establish it. Three times, then you're back to being considered now
to have a to bleed over longer periods of time. All right,
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר כל אשה שעברה עליה *Rabbi Eliezer omer
kol isha she'avra alei*, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* says
any woman, it doesn't even have to be a menopausal post-mean, I
mean a post-menopausal woman, any woman that goes 90 days without bleeding
is considered מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim *misulekes damim*. Now we actually mentioned
that it happens that, you know, women can stop having their period
based on like malnutrition or other causes, actually we're going to have
a case of malnutrition in a minute. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
*Rabbi Eliezer* said it doesn't have to be because of menopause, it
could be for any reason, if a woman has gone 90 days
without bleeding, whatever the causes are, we assume she's מסולקת דמים mesuleket
damim *misulekes damim* until we have evidence otherwise. So let's take a
look at the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, we're going to quote a ברייתא
*braita* we quoted before. תניא אמר amar, להם רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
לחכמים *Tanya amar lahem Rabbi Eliezer lachachamim*, the רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer.
*Rabbi Eliezer* said to the sages, מעשה בריבה אחת בהיטלו *ma'ase beriva
achas beHeitalu*, there was a story with a young woman in היטלו
*Heitalu*, name of a place, שהפסיקה שלשה עונות *shehifsika shelosha onos*, that
she went 90 days without bleeding, ובא מעשה לפני חכמים Chachamim *uva
ma'ase lifnei chachamim*, and then she apparently bled and they came to
the rabbis, ואמרו דייה שעתה dayah sha'atah. *ve'amru daya sha'ata*, she doesn't
have to be concerned 24 hours, she only has to be concerned
from the moment she saw because she's obviously מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim
*misulekes damim*, she had gone 90 days without bleeding. אמרו לו *Amru
lo*, so the rabbis said back to him, אין ein שעת הדחק
sha'at ha-dechak ראיה re'ayah. *ein sha'at hadechak re'aya*, that's not a proof,
that was an emergency situation so they were more lenient, it would
not be the general rule. מאי mai, שעת הדחק, sha'at ha-dechak what
was the sort of case of urgency? איכא דאמרי ika de-amri שני
בצורת הוו, shnei batzoret havo, so some say it was a time
of famine. So you see on the one hand, the time of
famine is why they didn't want to be so strict as to
say 24 hours, because then you'd have to throw out any תרומה
terumah that was handled in the last 24 hours by this woman,
and who wants to throw out any food at a time of
famine? But I also think it's significant that if it was a
time of famine, it explains why this woman, why this young woman
was stopped menstruating, because you know, malnutrition is a reason for a
stoppage of menstruating. Yes, Charlie.
The amount of loss it means to separate for תרומה terumah is
actually very, very small.
Well, sure, but if you have thousands of acres of wheat or
whatever.
And that shows how serious this famine must have been.
You mean because if you have a famine then you don't have
too much wheat so you don't have too much תרומה? terumah? Right.
That's an interesting point. Unless you have like תרומה terumah left stored
up from last year or something, but that's a good point.
But wouldn't, you know, שעת הדחק sha'at ha-dechak. we're saying like a
national שעת הדחק sha'at ha-dechak or do we have like?
Well, that's a good point because look at the next line. The
next line is much more of a local שעת הדחק. sha'at ha-dechak.
איכא דאמרי ika de-amri some say, no, טהרה אפישא לבידה. tahara apisha
lavidah. No, the שעת הדחק sha'at ha-dechak, was that in this one
case in the last 24 hours it happened to be that she
had done a lot of טהרות. taharot. This woman in this particular
case in the last 24 hours had done you know a hundred
pounds of תרומה. terumah. So that would be a much bigger consequence
of making her טמאה teme'ah for the last 24 hours than in
a normal case.
The entire wheat harvest.
Exactly. So in this case we took the more lenient position, but
it does not mean as a general rule we would agree with
this. As a general rule we would say even if a woman
went 90 days, if there's not a particular issue like she's post-menopausal,
we would not consider her to be מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim.
Yeah, like for instance you can have, you know, plentiful... I'm just
thinking about contemporary... I understand, someone's anorexic or whatever it is.
So I'm telling you, the second answer made it clear that even
if it was just because of this particular woman. Right. Not a
larger case.
Yes. So that means that whatever it is, it's a שעת הדחק.
sha'at ha-dechak. So in some ways, it's basically not a disagreement. I
mean if you really look at it, based on the second answer,
then anything would be a... I mean a woman wouldn't normally go
90 days without bleeding, so it would have to be a שעת
הדחק, sha'at ha-dechak, so it would be a ראיה.
No, I was the one that was connecting
the גמרא's Gemara description of the famine to the explanation why she
wasn't bleeding. That was not in the גמרא. Gemara All the גמרא
Gemara's was saying was that the rabbis, רבי Rebbi said, look, I'll
give you... not רבי, Rebbi רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. said look I'll
give you a proof that one time the rabbis ruled this, and
they said that was a special circumstance, there would have been a
lot of loss, okay? They weren't at all dealing with the question
of why she wasn't bleeding. Okay, that was not being discussed.
To me, like let's say she wasn't doing a lot of טהרות
taharot and for a reason she was just in dire straits, like
you know like her family had no food, and they would still
say that?
That I don't know, maybe that also would be a שעת הדחק.
sha'at ha-dechak. That's what I'm saying, so then if everything's שעת הדחק,
sha'at ha-dechak, then they're not really disagreeing over anything.
No, they're disagreeing about a case when it's a ten dollar loss
and not a hundred dollar loss. A standard case. That's what they're
disagreeing about.
But what I'm saying is, what's prompting her not to bleed which
presumably...
Who knows what's prompting her? I have no idea. But that doesn't
necessarily mean it's going to be a שעת הדחק. sha'at ha-dechak The
שעת הדחק, sha'at hadachak? your... the שעת הדחק sha'at hadachak? is that
how big of a loss is there? That's not necessarily linked to
why she's not bleeding, maybe in some cases it is. All right,
so let's go on. Yeah?
When a woman starts to bleed, anything she touched the previous?
Yes. So what we've been seeing since the beginning of the מסכת
masechet and then the question is how do you limit that? Because
as תוספות Tosafot has constantly pointed out, there's no way to be
careful for that. So, you know, it's a real like, you know,
it's a... so that's why the גמרא Gemara's sometimes tries to be
more lenient. But yeah, when a woman bleeds, since we're not certain,
maybe she only saw now, but maybe she started earlier. And particularly
because of the הלכה Halacha. that a woman becomes טמאה teme'ah from
the time the blood leaves, passes from the uterus through the cervix
into the vaginal canal. So even before it exits the woman's body,
just passes through the cervix, she's טמאה. teme'ah. So therefore you never
can know exactly when she became טמאה. teme'ah.
So there's בית שמאי Beit Shammai actually is quite lenient and בית
שמאי Beit Shammai is one of places, actually not בית שמאי, Beit
Shammai, שמאי, Shammai, that שמאי Shammai is much more lenient than הלל.
Hillel. He says you don't have to be concerned about any prior
time. But we actually, the sages here say that no, either till
24 hours back or till the last time she checked, whichever is
smaller. So that has enormous consequences because there's no way of protecting
against that. So then we are trying to say all the cases
where we wouldn't have to be concerned. But yeah, but that's exactly
why there's like, you know, there's nothing you can do to prevent
this. Okay, what are you going to do? Never handle טהרות? taharot?
You know, so it's pretty... You could always check right before... a
woman could always check right before she handles
טהרות, taharot, which was...
Right. So yeah, exactly. All right, so let's take a look.
וחשו רבנן להפסד טהרות, va-chashu rabanan le-hefsed taharot, and the rabbis were
concerned about the loss of טהרה. tahara. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, מעשה
ועשה רבי כרבי אליעזר. ma'aseh ve-asah Rebbi ke-Rabbi Eliezer. Once רבי Rebbi
ruled like רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer, that said you don't have to
be concerned 24 hours back with this woman. לאחר שנזכר, le-achar she-nizkar,
once he remembered that he shouldn't have ruled that way, אמר, we
had quoted this before, כדי רבי אליעזר לסמוך עליו בשעת הדחק. kedai
Rabbi Eliezer lismoch alav be-sha'at ha-dechak. You know what? We can rely
on רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer even in a... at a time of
urgency. So, you know, it's after the fact, we might as well
just keep
it.
So who cares if it's a time of like you know pressure
of urgency of a special circumstances. If his position is rejected, then
you can never rely on it. So אלא דלא איתמר הלכתא לא
כמר ולא כמר. ela delo itmar hilchata lo kemar velo kemar. It
wasn't... it wasn't like we completely rejected his opinion. We didn't have
an explicit ruling how we go like and ומאי לאחר שנזכר? u'mai
le'achar shenizkar? And then what does it mean that he remembered he
made a mistake? What mistake did he make? ומאי לאחר שנזכר? u'mai
le'achar shenizkar? What did he remember? לאחר שנזכר דלאו יחיד פליג עליה
אלא רבים פליג עליה. le'achar shenizkar delav yachid palig alei ela rabim
palig alei. Once he remembered, you know what, it wasn't a one-on-one
debate; most of the positions disagreed with Rabbi Eliezer. So although there
wasn't like black-letter law that we rule against Rabbi Eliezer, the normal
conclusion would have been if you would have applied the normal types
of ways of deciding, you would have concluded against Rabbi Eliezer, but
it hadn't been formally ruled. So he realized that he should have
ruled against it, but it wasn't like it was a formally rejected
opinion.
So then he said, you know what,
כדאי רבי אליעזר לסמוך עליו בשעת הדחק. kedai Rabbi Eliezer lismoch alav
besha'at hadachak. It's a special case, I might as well rely on
him. Now this is extremely important. I mentioned we had this quoted
before because there's a general idea in הלכה Halacha. which is, you
know, you can rely on a דעת יחיד. da'at yachid. One of
the reasons we quote minority opinions is you can rely on minority
opinions בשעת הדחק. besha'at hadachak. But the question becomes, well, a, one
question is what do you define as a שעת הדחק? sha'at hadachak
But the other question is, when is it still a minority opinion
and what does it become a rejected opinion? And you see here
that tension in the גמרא. Gemara. Is it ruled that way, or
is it just the normal conclusion would have led this way? So
for example, there's a whole interesting discussion that comes around, you know,
what happens once the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch rules? How canonical and
absolutely authoritative is the שולחן ערוך? Shulchan Aruch? You know, and if
the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch rules against an opinion, but let's say
it has a lot of support earlier in the ראשונים, Rishonim, does
it remain a דעת יחיד da'at yachid that you can rely on
בשעת הדחק? besha'at hadachak? Let's say the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch quotes
the opinion but rejects it. יש אומרים Yesh omrim this, but this
is the הלכה. halakhah, You know, when does something still remain a
minority opinion, when is it considered rejected, becomes very important, and you
see the גמרא Gemara's here is dealing with that balancing act, that
it's one thing to say this is how the normal conclusion would
have gone, but that's another thing to say we've actually formally ruled
that way and rejected the other opinion. Now what is the שעת
הדחק? sha'at hadachak. So if you say the שעת הדחק sha'at hadachak
was like this case of a famine, so then the point is,
but then why did he make a mistake? It looks like even
the חכמים Chachamim agree in a שעת הדחק. sha'at hadachak So תוספות
Tosafot says that it's not as bad as the שעת הדחק sha'at
hadachak before. And actually I mentioned last time תוספות Tosafot gives one
interesting explanation that the שעת הדחק sha'at hadachak had a lot more
to do with רבי Rabbi. than the person he was פסק'ינג paskening
for. And תוספות Tosafot says that the שעת הדחק sha'at hadachak, was
he gave a ruling and then the person left, and the person
lived, let's say, I don't know, three towns over. And then when
he remembered, if he needed to reverse himself, he would have had
to go three towns over to reverse himself. So it was his
שעת הדחק that he didn't want to
שלעפּ shlep out there.
So that was an interesting explanation of תוספות Tosafot because if it
was a more serious שעת הדחק, it seems like even the חכמים
agree that they're willing to sort of, you know, be lenient in
that type of a case. Yes.
Well, similar to the שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, there's the issue of
the רמ"א's Rema rulings.
Well, that's what I meant, שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch רמ"א. Rema.
And there are many cases where we אשכנזים Ashkenazim don't seem to
follow the רמ"א. Rema.
Yes, but that's like you see that's diff- well, you're correct, meaning
that gets to the question about how authoritative is the שולחן ערוך
Shulchan Aruch when like a lot of the פוסקים Poskim contemporary and
immediately after reject the פסק psak of the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch
or the רמ"א, Rema, then you could sort of say that never
sort of became sort of established in הלכה. halakhah? But what if
there's actually a position that was followed, that was ruled and then
followed? You know, to what degree are other positions still viable? But
you're right, that's a lot much larger discussion. Okay,
דחוק. Dachuk. Well, דחק Dachak literally means pressure. So means like there's
somehow it's
extenuating circumstances is a good, yes, is a very good. I was
going to say some case of exigency, but extenuating circumstances, you know,
so some, right.
Next שיעור Shiur learning.
Right. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. תינוקת שלא הגיע זמנה לראות. Tinoket shelo
higia zemana lirot. Now before we talked about a woman that was
sort of becoming postmenopausal, stopping and starting again and so on. Now
we're going to talk at the opposite end about a young girl
who has not yet reached the age of puberty, the age where
she's expecting her period, וראתה vera'ata and she still sees. So now
פעם ראשונה דיה שעתה. Pa'am rishona dayah sha'atah. The first time we're
not concerned twenty-four hours back, it was a fluke. שניה דיה שעתה.
Shniya dayah sha'atah. The second time as well, we're not, why? Normally
we say that once a woman bleeds, now we assume that that
she should expect to be bleeding. But this is a woman who
even if she bled, she's... I mean a woman, she's a girl,
she's ten years old. So it's even after the first time it's
a fluke and we don't say oh now we see she's starting
to get her period because she's... she's not yet of that age.
So even the second time we would not yet be concerned that
she should be expecting her period. However, שלישית, shlishit, by the time
she sees three times, even if she's very young, then we see
that okay, she's getting her period even at a very young age.
והרי היא ככל הנשים. veharei hi kechol hanashim. she's like all other
women that מטמאה מעת לעת mitamei me'eis le'eis what she has to
worry twenty-four hours back now that we see it's not a total
fluke and she is starting to get her period. Right exactly. Well
but no it doesn't say that that's in a fixed way. We
said before even not fixed. Once it's three times we see that
it's not we see that she's not מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim. You
can prove you're not מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim. without having a וסת
קבוע veset kavua right we said that earlier about the 90, 91,
93 and so on. So once she sees three times we know
she's
regular that she's not מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim. even though she's very
young.
That's also an interesting case because the age has
preceded over the centuries and I
think the average age of menarche was what
I think below twelve? Twelve. Twelve, but it used to be
and maybe even less. Right. Yeah so Charlie mentioned that until 150
years
ago mostly for 17, 17.
But yeah but that's because of malnutrition. Malnutrition, yeah. Right but in
the time as Charlie was telling us yesterday in the time that
the גמרא Gemara was written actually the standard of living was much
higher.
So that actually over the last few decades it's gone down.
Yeah. Yeah. Doesn't that also is that also related to like also
like fast food and all that other bad stuff people are eating?
McDonald's cheeseburgers are amazing.
Right that's what I remember hearing. McDonald's French fries?
Yeah.
It's the hormone that they put in the cows.
Oh interesting.
That's why you should buy organic.
Okay. All right.
Now okay moving on.
Now אמר רב נחמן Amar Rav Nachman so he's now now I
should stop at this moment and say the גמרא's Gemara going to
allude to a debate of רבי Rebbi. and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel which it won't get into detail here but
we'll get into it later which is how many times does something
have to repeat to be a חזקה? chazakah? We normally say three
but that's actually the opinion of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel. רבי Rebbi says even twice already establishes a pattern. The
גמרא's Gemara going to assume that this is actually going like רבי
Rebbi because after the second time she's proven that she's regular so
that for we're concerned by the third time we're concerned that you
know we're already concerned that now she is will be regularly bleeding
so therefore we're concerned twenty-four hours back after twice. So although you
could have said no once it's third the very time that proves
that she's regular is also the time we're concerned backwards. It's not
you see the point it's not exactly clear which is the pattern.
Is the pattern two and therefore we're concerned for the next time?
Or is the pattern three and therefore we're concerned by for the
time that the pattern was established? But anyway we'll talk about it
in the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא's Gemara going to assume the former
that the pattern was two and therefore the third time we say
ah this was a three her seeing that was part of a
regular pattern or part of a woman that's not מסולקת דמים mesuleket
damim. and therefore we're concerned backwards.
So you just saw it like thirty days and after sixty days
and after six months and we see she's a regular pattern?
Well not six months that creates a מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim again
but like thirty, forty, twenty then yes. That's not a regular pattern
of וסת קבוע veset kavua but she's no longer מסולקת דמים mesuleket
damim. that's what we saw before. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara
goes on to say the following the ברייתא I should say. Okay
שלישית הרי היא ככל הנשים ומטמאה מעת לעת ומפקידה לפקידה. Shlishis harei
hi k'chol hanashim u'mitamei me'eis le'eis u'mipikida lifkida. עברו עליה שלוש עונות.
Avru aleha shalosh onos. Now this woman she went she's a woman
10 years old. Okay she saw three months in a row. Now
she went 90 days and she didn't see. So remember we saw
that 90 days certainly by a woman that's menopause post-menopausal and for
רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer. for any woman 90 days re-establishes that you're
מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim, So she went 90 days so this 10-year-old
is now back to being מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim וראתה Verasa and
she bled again דיה שעתה dayah sha'atah so she doesn't it's enough
what she saw she doesn't have to worry backwards because she goes
back to being מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim, ועוד עברו עליה שלוש עונות
וראתה Ve'od avru aleha shalosh onos verasa now another 90 days so
now she goes back again to being מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim So
again דיה שעתה. dayah sha'atah. ועוד עברו עליה שלוש עונות וראתה Ve'od
avru aleha shalosh onos verasa another 90 days so again she went
back to being מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim So again she sees וראתה
verasa now we don't say דיה שעתה dayah sha'atah because now she
went 90 days, 90 days, 90 days right it's like we said
before now she's got a pattern of 90 days gaps and therefore
הרי היא ככל הנשים ומטמאה מעת לעת ומפקידה לפקידה. harei hi k'chol
hanashim u'mitamei me'eis le'eis u'mipikida lifkida. She worries back twenty-four hours. וכשהגיע
זמן לראות פעם ראשונה. U'keshe'higia zman lir'os pa'am rishona. Now you know
what let me start illustrating this on the board.
Okay
so here's a woman she's 10 years old young girl. Okay so
she sees time one right and then she is considered still
still דיה שעתה dayah sha'atah right because she's still מסולקת דמים mesuleket
damim. it hasn't proven that she's you know that she is getting
her period. Then thirty days it's still דיה שעתה. dayah sha'atah. Okay
then here so we've got one, two, three so then it starts
saying that now you have the twenty-four hour window. Okay because now
she's regular. Okay then what happens is she goes 90 days. So
she goes 90 days alright and now she is now she's again
מסולקת mesuleket right if So she's מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim. So although
here she was going 24 hours, now she bleeds again, and again
we say דייה שעתה dayah sha'atah. because this was a restart. Okay,
this is a like a reboot okay because it went 90 days.
So even though here she was waiting 24 hours, here it goes
back to דייה שעתה. dayah sha'atah, Then another 90 days, so it's
another reboot, right? Because here she's okay and therefore again she sees
and it's דייה שעתה. dayah sha'atah But she goes another 90 days,
so now we have one, two, three, we have three types of
seeing in a pattern, the same way here we have like three
seeing, and even if this pattern is inexact, you can no longer
say it's a reboot because now we see the 90 days or
even if it's 91 and 93, even if it's inexact, it basically
proves that she's this is not making her מסולקת דמים, mesuleket damim
it's just very long patterns, so then she goes back to being
24 hours.
Okay, but she similarly in the middle though, she had a 30,
but the
גמרא's Gemara going to ask that.
Okay, the reason I'm drawing this is because it's about to get
more complicated.
So let's take a look. That's why there are these huge דרשות.
drashas. Okay so anyway, let's take a look. Okay. וכשהגיע זמנה לראות
פעם ראשונה. ve'khishe'higia zemanah lirot pa'am rishonah. Now, if she so now
she has 90 days, 90 days, 90 days, so when her time
so okay, now period. Okay, so that's that. Now let's say it's
not a 10-year-old girl, let's say it's a 12-year-old girl, a 13-year-old
girl. הגיע זמנה לראות, higia zemanah lirot, so she's it's her time
where she would reasonably say she hasn't had her period yet but
her body is ready. Then פעם ראשונה דייה שעתה, pa'am rishonah dayah
sha'atah, the first time it still hasn't started yet. So the first
time it's still you don't worry 24 hours back. But שנייה, sheniyah,
by the second time, this is a girl who's ready to have
her period, so once she sees one, you say now she's getting
her period, so by the second time מטמאה מעת לעת ומפקידה לפקידה,
metamei mei'eit le'eit umipikidah lifikidah, then you worry 24 hours back. And
the same הלכה, halakhah? if you start having 90 day breaks.
עברה שלושה עונות וראתה, avarah sheloshah onot ve'ra'atah, if this young girl
now who is ready to get her period, she started but then
she had a 90 day break, דייה שעתה, dayah sha'atah, it goes
back to a reboot and it goes back to דייה שעתה dayah
sha'atah. because now she's מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim. again. Okay, now we're
going to look at the first case which we drew up on
the board which is more complicated. אמר מר עברה שלושה עונות דייה
שעתה. amar mar avarah sheloshah onot dayah sha'atah. So when she went
these this first reboot here, this 90 days, דייה שעתה, dayah shaatah,
she only had to worry about the time she saw. So says
the גמרא Gemara top of י"ח ע"א. Yud-Chet Amud-Aleph. חזרה וחזתה בעונתה
מאי? chazarah ve'hazatah be'onot mai?
This is Michael's always anticipating the גמרא. Gemara Let's say instead of
here another reboot, let's say here she actually saw after 30 days.
What would be the הלכה? halacha Okay, that's the גמרא's Gemara question.
Now what is this question?
Here's let me trace for you what the question is.
Okay, a normal girl as we saw, וכשהגיע זמנה לראות, ve'khishe'higia zemanah
lirot, that it's her time that she's already you know of an
age of puberty. Okay, the first time she's not concerned backwards, the
second time she is. This girl, the reason she has three times
before she had to be concerned backwards is because she hadn't gotten
to the age of
puberty, right? You're with me?
So now here, how do we treat this case? She has proven
that she is starting to have her cycle. But then there was
a reboot. At this stage, after the reboot, is her status like
a girl who is not at the age of puberty because you
know physically she's still 10 years old? Or is her status like
a girl that is at the age of
puberty because although there was a reboot, we see from back here
that she does start having her period? So which category do we
put her in, right? When she's had saw three times and then
had the reboot. Is she in the category of a girl who
does get her you know is of the age or is not
of the age of puberty? What difference does it make? If you
consider her of the age of puberty, so by the second time
she sees, she starts worrying 24 hours back. If you consider her
not of the age of puberty, like it was a complete reboot,
then she'll only start worrying 24 hours back until she saw three
times. So this is a reboot, but that's not so interesting. What's
obviously a reboot you're only going to be concerned after the month.
The question is without a reboot she sees 30 days later, is
this like a girl under the age of puberty that you're not
concerned by the second time, or is it like a girl of
the age of puberty that you are concerned by the second time?
Good question. That's the גמרא's Gemara question.
Right. Let's let's see the answer and then I'll take your question.
Okay so מאי, what's the הלכה? halacha אמר רב גידל אמר רב
פעם ראשונה ושנייה דייה שעתה שלישית מטמאה מעת לעת ומפקידה לפקידה. amar
Rav Gidel amar Rav pa'am rishonah u'sheniyah dayah sha'atah shelishit metamei mei'eit
le'eit umipikidah lifikidah. He basically says that she it is a complete
reboot. She's like a girl under the age of puberty.
So he says פעם ראשונה pa'am rishonah this time ושנייה ve'sheniyah even
if she bleeds here after 30 days דייה שעתה. dayah shaatah. It's
like a complete reboot, she goes back to being treated as if
she's under the age of puberty and therefore even the second ראייה
re'iyah it's not a problem. The only time it starts being a
problem is after three. The same way here one two it wasn't
a problem backwards until the third, here too it's a complete reboot,
one two he was without ninety days would not be a problem
backwards until there was third.
Even if the third was ninety days later then she'd be back
to מסולקת דמים, right?
Well, that we're going to get to that in a minute. Okay,
but anyway, but that's going to be the next רש"י. Rashi. Okay,
so basically you really did not need the ninety days to say
דייה שעתה, dayah shaatah והרא"ש veHaRosh discusses and why did we give
that example, so because we should just say that makes a pattern
and that it's whatever different. Even after, even after thirty days is
what the complete restart and it's and it's דייה שעתה.
dayah shaatah Okay, those
two different situations for the first 30 30,
this? No, no, all the way to the right. Is that a
separate situation or is that part of this?
No, that's all the same the same girl. Okay, so that's the
question. Here it was only a concern backwards after three times, after
this period of ninety days, is that a complete reboot or not?
And the answer is it is a complete reboot. So therefore you
need only the third time you'll be concerned. One, two, you're still
not concerned backwards and then on the third. What's the logic? What's
the logic?
That's still a girl who's under puberty.
So if even though this proved maybe the evidence proved that she
was getting her period, but then you had immediate counter-evidence.
So the two sort of balance themselves out.
So you treat the rule that she should not yet be having
her period exactly even though the specific circumstance tells you otherwise.
No, but this circumstance told you otherwise but then she went ninety
days without getting her period.
That's actually normal biology. Is it?
Yeah. הגמרא Hagemara didn't look at it that way.
In here is very rarely regular. In general. Could really go like
ninety days? Yeah, and that's that is the normal trajectory. So these
cases are
pretty normal. It would if we didn't think that it would be
we'd be very suspicious of bleeding in a ten-year-old if we didn't
think she was beginning
her
puberty a little bit early. Right, right. We'd think she had an
illness.
I mean right I understand
it would be a problem.
So that's interesting. So it seems like the גמרא Gemara right.
It's its logic. It's its biology.
I would say two things and this came up yesterday as well.
Either the גמרא Gemara like me being a man didn't know that
biology right and didn't aware that that's normal. So it would assume
that the fact that it went ninety days proves that it was
a fluke and it was not yet the starting of it. That's
one thing that just didn't know the biology. The other possibility is
and this is an interesting question, maybe it's going by certain formal
rules despite the biology. So if you have a formal rule that
ninety days determines
מסולקת דמים maybe that just in a formal way counteracts what happened
prior. But I think probably the former has a lot to do
with it as well at least personally.
And these days we do that all her cycles a lot right.
We have pills now that can give you periods maybe three or
four times a year. Right. So a woman could change her status.
Yes. Well, but again as we've seen if you have your ninety
days does not make you מסולקת דמים if you regularly see with
that type of a gap. So you just have longer periods but
it would not be מסולקת דמים. That's why when it repeats three
times you go it's no longer מסולקת דמים. Yeah.
And women are quoted not that infrequently in ש"ס. Shas.
Right. We will see places in נדה Niddah where women are quoted
as philosophers about thing. Yeah. So we'll see though. I mean it's
its relatively it's pretty infrequent even though it's מסכת נדה Masechet Niddah
and when it is we'll see the weight that it's given. So
okay. But nature is very irregular first years.
That's exactly although see see you you knew this like it was
like it was obvious to you but to us it's a חידוש.
I think it's so common. I also don't have any daughters I
must state.
Although
although what they're mainly talking about here is טהרה taharah right rather
than but
it's based on the question of do we have to be concerned
that it occurred and is it a pattern? Okay let's keep on
going. Okay that's point is very well taken. Yeah go ahead.
Is it obvious she's still considered pre-pubescent for דייה שעתה after those
ninety days?
No
because this we're going to say in a minute this is going
according to רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer. So any woman who was ninety
days, like we said before, any woman who hasn't seen for ninety
days is considered דייה שעתה even if she's whatever age she is.
Okay? All right, but it's a good point but the גמרא Gemara
is going to say it's רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer. Let's keep on
going. ואמר Veamar now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay that
was his answer.
So was the גמרא Gemara at all concerned with why? I mean
all these הלכות halachot are based on this idea that you're supposed
around thirty days have cycles and and they know that. They
know
that.
Whether
the גמרא Gemara does speculate and that it said yesterday or assumed
like oh when she's
nursing—were you here yesterday? So you know when she's nursing it thinks
that she's not bleeding because it thinks the blood is turning into
milk. You know when she's pregnant it thinks she's not nursing because
she thinks that the sort of right the physical weariness of the
pregnancy causes the blood to go away. So it did sort of
speculate on certain correlations.
It wouldn't link it with
disease or anything like that?
They wouldn't look at it from—Not generally.
I mean especially if it's something that they sort of you know
knew occurred. I mean the גמרא Gemara does sometimes talk about מחמת
חרדה machmat charada fear anxiety.
So I mean what time you mean with the גמרא Gemara say
I think you need to see a doctor? Yeah. That's a good
point. I don't know of a case like that. I mean the
גמרא Gemara does have a case about somebody who's bleeding מחמת מכה
machmat maka because of a wound. So it does sort of acknowledge
that that can be the case. So anyway but it's a good
point. But that's normally when there's some supporting evidence to indicate that
there's some internal wound. Okay so let's see the גמרא Gemara continues.
ועוד ראתה ג' עונות ופרסה v'od ra'ata gimmel onot u'pirsa now we're
going to the next period.
דיה שעתה. daya sha'ata. הדר חזיא בעונות מאי. hadar chazya b'onot mai.
So first we asked after this does she go back to being
like prepubescent and what would happen when she'd bleed here? And the
answer is yes she does go back and דיה שעתה. daya sha'ata.
Now we're saying she bled one, two and now—so not the 30
days every 90 days after two 90-day periods and then we said
after another 90
days היא דיה שעתה hi daya sha'ata backwards. But what if she
bled here? Okay what would be the הלכה halacha there? Meaning what
do we say? Do we say this is again a reboot? So
since this reboot what did we say by this reboot? By this
reboot we said she goes
back to being prepubescent and it's דיה שעתה. daya sha'ata. So maybe
after this reboot we'll say the same thing. She goes back to
being treated prepubescent and again it's דיה שעתה. daya sha'ata. Or do
we say no like you only get one reboot? Okay so if
you had this you can go back to your earlier status. But
now you've bled three times here, bled two
more times, we're not going to say even though it went 90
days we're not going to say you go back to being prepubescent
and this bleeding we're going to say is now 24 hours. Okay
that's the question. Here we could say after three and then one
this is a full reboot it goes back to 24 hours even
the second time.
The גמרא Gemara, tells the story after that happened twice. That's the
question and let's see what the answer is.
אמר רב כהנא אמר רב גידל אמר רב amar Rav Kahana amar
Rav Gidal amar Rav פעם ראשונה דיה שעתה שנייה מטמאה מעת לעת
ומפקידה לפקידה. pa'am rishona daya sha'ata shniya metamei me'et l'et u'mipkida l'pkida.
So it said you're right.
You're right. By this time we're not going to do a full
reboot. So this is going to be דיה שעתה daya sha'ata because
it was after 90 days but here you're no longer considered by
this time you're no longer considered prepubescent and by this time a
normal girl who it's her time to be bleeding by the second
time she is חושש 24 hours now. Okay?
So this is a full reboot you could call it. So you
go back to being prepubescent so when you do it here it's
דיה שעתה. daya sha'ata. But this is not a full reboot. This
only means that after this you're considered already to have been at
the age of seeing and therefore it's 24 hours back by the
second time.
It is 24 hours now, not only. Yeah. Exactly. Because it's a
second? Yeah because once we can say the first three were maybe
a fluke,
Rachel's point aside, the biology aside, but once it's not only you
saw three times but then you saw again and again even though
it was this 90-day break clearly you're not at that status at
all. No it's a reboot in the sense that
in the sense that this is דיה שעתה.
daya sha'ata. If it weren't a reboot at all then it would
be 24 hours. Actually it's a good point. Oh you know what?
James makes an excellent point.
Since we see that here even after 30 days it's דיה שעתה
daya sha'ata you don't need a reboot to get this to be
דיה שעתה. daya sha'ata. Right it's already there. Which actually supports why
we're waiting here 24 hours right? You don't actually need that to
serve as a reboot.
All right anyway let's go on. But under other circumstances it would.
Anyway let's go on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. All
right that was the hard part. It gets easier after this. Okay.
מני
רבי היא. mani Rabbi hi. Now who is this? This the fact
that after two times as I said to you the גמרא gemara
assumes that because the third time you wait back 24 hours it
proves that two times establishes the pattern. Okay? And therefore that's therefore
the third time becomes a 24-hour concern. So who is that? That's
רבי. Rebbi, דאמר בתרי זימני הוי חזקה d'amar betrei zimnei havei chazaka
after twice we've established a pattern. אימא סיפא eima seifa let's look
at the end.
עברו עליה שלש עונות וראתה דיה שעתה. avru aleha shalosh onot v'ra'ata
daya sha'ata. So it says a girl we've already been saying 90
days is a— It's even more explicit at the end. The end
it says even when a girl it's her has hit puberty and
it's her time to see and she begins seeing with a 30-day
break, she goes back to saying דיה שעתה, Daya sha'atah, not a
30-day, a 90-day break. So who's the opinion that says that no
matter who for all women once it's a 90-day break they go
back to דיה שעתה? Daya sha'atah? That's רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer? right?
We could say before that for a post-menopausal woman 90 days is
a reboot, or for a woman that's under age 90 days is
some type of a reboot, but רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says for
all women 90 days makes her מסולקת דמים and that was the
case at the end because it said even a woman, a girl
that it's her time to see, after 90 days she's מסולקת דמים.
So now it's רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer. So what's the big deal?
So the idea that you go by patterns of two is רבי.
Rebbi. The idea that you have a 90-day reboot is רבי אליעזר.
Rebbi Eliezer? And the problem is, if you remember we said a
minute ago that רבי Rebbi basically decided that the הלכה wasn't like
רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer. So how could this משנה Mishna both be
רבי Rebbi and רבי אליעזר? Rebbi Eliezer? Okay, different points, but how
could it be this way? So let's take a look. וכי תימא
רבי היא, Vachi teima Rebbi hi, that it is רבי, Rebbi ובעונות
סבר לה כרבי אליעזר. uva'onos savar lah k'Rebbi Eliezer. So the fact
that it says two times establishes a pattern is רבי. Rebbi. The
fact that it says 90 days is a reboot, that's רבי אליעזר
Rebbi Eliezer. and he ruled like רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer. ומי סבר
לה? Umi savar lah? Says how can you say רבי Rebbi, rules
like רבי אליעזר? Rebbi Eliezer, והא לאחר שנזכר אמר, Veha le'achar shenizkar
amar, it says that רבי Rebbi remembered that he shouldn't have been
ruling like רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer So how could this ברייתא assume
both רבי Rebbi. and רבי Rebbi אליעזר? So goes the opposite way.
אלא רבי אליעזר היא. Ela Rebbi Eliezer hi. The author of the
ברייתא is רבי Rebbi אליעזר. That's the 90-day reboot. ובזמנים סבר לה
כרבי. Ubizmanim savar lah k'Rebbi. And he holds that after, but he
happens also to פסקן pasken that patterns are established after two times
like רבי. rebbe. Okay, so that's basically the point of bringing in
this very complicated, other than the הלכה itself, is that we see
that a pattern is established after twice. So the third time it's
considered regular and you wait back 24 hours. And the fact that
90 days is a reboot even for people, girls that are at
the period where they should be seeing, so that's רבי rebbe, אליעזר.
So part רבי rebbe אליעזר, part רבי, and therefore it's רבי אליעזר
who's ruling like רבי when it comes to establishing patterns. Okay, now
we're going to ask some other questions.
As if that wasn't enough. כתם שבין ראשונה ושנייה טהור. Kesem shebein
rishona v'shniya tahor.
If a woman sees a stain, כתם, kesem, okay,
between ראשונה ושנייה, rishona v'shniya, okay. She sees a stain actually,
we don't even have to worry about that. Okay. This is a
woman who's not regular, who is not yet a חזקת chezkas seeing,
a young girl, right? So until she sees three times we don't
assume that she, we assume it's a total fluke. So if somewhere
here she finds a כתם, kesem, a
stain, she saw once, she actually had her period first time, ten
years old, and then she finds a stain on her garment a
month later. So she doesn't have to assume it came from her.
Again, we discussed כתמים. kesamim. It was a time where we're not
talking about inside of a tight fitting underwear, we're talking about like
on some, you know, inner flap of her garment, you know, there
was blood all around those places between the chickens they were slaughtering
and all this type of stuff was not very hygienic. So there's
a reasonable assumption, even if you don't know specifically, that it might
not have come from her. And since it's a total fluke, she
can assume that that's טהור. tahor. Okay, between the first and the
second. The question is how about between the second and the third?
Because if she actually saw, like we said that after twice you've
established a pattern, like רבי. And if you actually saw a third
time, she saw, she would be assumed concerned it was her since
it's now part of a pattern and have to be concerned 24
hours back. So if by the third time she's concerned that she
has a regularity, a pattern, so if she sees a כתם, kesem,
maybe she also has to be concerned that it came from her.
Or maybe not. Maybe until she actually treats her period as regular,
which happens at the third time, she doesn't yet have to treat
her כתם, kesem, stain, as having come from her. Okay, so that
is the question about seeing a stain between two and three.
So let's take a look. Okay, שבין שנייה ושלישית. shebein shniya v'shlishis.
So what if it's a stain between second and third? So she's
not yet treated any bleeding as טמא, tamei, as, you know, part
of a pattern, but she has been, but she's ready to do
it because she's done it twice and she's established a pattern. חזקיה
אמר טמא, Chizkiyah amar tamei, so we'll treat the כתם kesem like,
like, like an actual, you know, normal case of seeing blood and
it's טמא. tamei. רבי יוחנן אמר טהור. Rebbi Yochanan amar tahor. No,
I'm not yet going to attribute it to her. She has not
yet had it three times. חזקיה אמר טמא, Chizkiyah amar tamei, כיון
דאילו חזיא מיטמיא. keivan d'ilu chazya mitamya.
So since were she to bleed she would be טמא, tamei, and
not only טמא, tamei, she's always טמא tamei when she bleeds, but
she'd see that as bleeding as regular and therefore be concerned 24
hours backwards, not as a fluke. If she's going to see a
third time it would not be treated as a fluke. So כתמה
נמי טמא, kisma nami tamei, even when she sees a stain it's
going to be seen as coming from her and therefore טמא. tamei.
רבי יוחנן אמר טהור. Rebbi Yochanan amar tahor. No, I'm not going
to treat the stain yet as טמא, tamei, it's טהור. tahor. Why?
כיון ד keivan d... אתחזקה בדם, it-chazka bedam,
since she has not yet established a pattern by blood. Now that
sounds like you need three times to establish a pattern, but רש״י
Rashi says again fitting into the earlier discussion of רבי of two
times, yes she has a pattern but it has not yet been
applied. She has not yet had a bleeding that she has set
is sort of is part of a pattern. Only by the third
time, although it's proven by the second time, it's only sort of
treated as a pattern the third time. So since it has not
yet given that status to real blood, כשם נמי לא מטמאינן לה,
keshem nami lo metameinan lah, we don't treat the כתם ketham as
coming from her, we don't know where it came from yet. And
so therefore since we're not have not yet treated her bleeding as
as regular, we're not going to treat the the stain as coming
from her. Rivka?
Thanks, I was just wondering with the
ten-year-old girl, is she going to come at the authority...
Yeah, that's a very good question. How much was this something? So
the גמרא gemara had a story about two days ago about a
about a maidservant, a slave woman of רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, that
had a situation and then went and asked רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel.
But again, that was a maidservant, you know, that was not this
may be very different between mothers and daughters and so on. Right.
Right, right. So, yeah, I don't know. I don't know if we
have any evidence about, you know, I mean there are
women able to answer these questions.
So you have a גמרא gemara that discusses the question about women
dealing with identifying whether something is actually red and considered blood or
not, and that's going to come up much later. Right, exactly. Whether
you have this issue about like women, you know, sort of saying,
oh in this case you have to be concerned 24 hours back,
in this case you don't. I don't know. I think we have
very few cases of strewn in all מסכת נדה Masechet Niddah that
it came up to the rabbis for women's voices. So even as
women as asking rabbi שאלות, shaylos, you know, when were these how
were these cases presented? Were they presented to other women? Were they
presented to the rabbis? We we can keep a scorecard. Seriously, I
don't I can't think off the top of my head. I understand.
I understand. Right. So how much were the women handling this? Look,
I I think you're right. I mean, let's count as we're going
through the מסכתא. Masecha. So far we have one case where רבי's
maidservant asked, not רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel maidservant
asked him. Let's
that's the only case so far we have of an actual question
being asked. So I think I think it's a good question, but
look for it as we go through. I don't know off the
top of my head the answer to that.
Oh, isn't there another place that women...
report accurately?
Well, that's a general issue, you know, the גמרא, gemara I mean,
the גמרא Gemara in the beginning of what do you call it,
of גיטין, Gittin, you know, in other places establishes the idea that
עד אחד נאמן באיסורין, eid echad ne'eman b'issurin, that you trust one
witness, one person about like is the food you're eating kosher? I
can go to your house, you tell me it's kosher, I can
trust you. And one of the proofs that they give for this,
well one of the proofs is the fact, you know, רש״י Rashi
there says it, is the fact like every single day we trust
our wives when they tell us that they're feeding us kosher food,
you know? And they point to the fact that the תורה, Torah,
that the, you know, נדה Niddah is another evidence that that women
are trusted to to tell what their status is.
But you and I both know that women do not have a
status of an עד. eid.
Right, so the עד אחד נאמן באיסורין eid echad ne'eman b'issurin is
not classic testimony in court. It's basically an issue about believability, and
it's true for women as well, that when it comes to an
issue about is something kosher or טריף, treif, אסור assur or מותר,
muttar, any person is believed. It's not about formal rules of עדות.
eidus. And one of the classic proof examples of that is a
woman's believability about her own status vis-a-vis נדה. Niddah.
So that actually you're right, that actually but I'm saying, not only
is it true, for many ראשונים Rishonim that is the sort of
foundation of the principle that you believe one person when it comes
to statuses of kosher, טריף, treif, אסור, assur, and מותר, muttar, is
the fact that the woman is believed about her own status as
a נדה, Niddah, yes.
And that issue just just only apply to people who are above
בר או בת
מצוה
bar
or bat mitzvah age?
Yeah, so that's...
because then we have ten-year-olds and that's...
Right. All right, I'm going to bracket that. Okay. All right, so
now let's keep on going. מתקי לה רבי אילא.
Matki lah
Rabbi Ila.
So רבי אילא Rabbi Ila asks: ומה בין זו לבתולה שדמיה טהורים.
u'mai bein zo l'betula she-dameha tehorim. So now
חזקיהו Chizkiyahu said, right, that if she bleeds by the third time,
the we assume the כתם ketham came for... excuse me, she bled
twice, we assume the כתם ketham came from her, even though she's
an underaged girl and she has yet to bleed three times. He
says, how is this different then a בתולה betula after her wedding
night? If she has stains, we assume those stains are not from
her because basically we assume a woman after her wedding night depends
on how old she is and whatever, we'll get to that פרק,
perek, but we assume that she's going to have a certain amount
of bleeding based on the hymenal bleed, okay. And therefore if there's
a stain, we don't make that טמא. tamei. So why is it
by that woman we assume that if it's a stain it's, you
know, she's
טהור, tahor, because we said the hymenal bleeding, and this woman who's
a prepubescent... We are concerned about the stain. Now the answer is
obviously different and let's see what the גמרא'ס gemara's answer is. אמר
ליה amar lei רב זירא Rav Zeira זו zu צירפא tzirpa מצויה
metzuya וזו v'zu אין צירפא tzirpa מצויה. metzuya. So first of all
the metaphor here is the sap, okay, like you know, it's a
tree that the sap is running through, that's sort of the metaphor
for the blood for the woman and her menstruation. So it says
by the virgin she we
actually she is bleeding but it's not menstrual bleeding, it's hymenal bleeding.
So we can say her stains are טהור tahor because we could
say it came from her but it was from hymenal blood. So
that's why we can say they're טהור. tahor. This woman, we it's
not like she has another source of blood. It's not like she's
got some other reason to be bleeding. And therefore if there's blood
we'll assume it's from her, there's nothing else you can attribute it
to, so you're going to say that she is טמאה. tmeia. So
there's a big difference when you have a positive a concrete other
thing that explains where the blood is coming from that's not טמא
tamei as opposed to this woman, although she's pre-pubescent, she has bled
twice and there's nothing else to attribute it to. Okay. אמר עולא
אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק: Amar Ulla amar Rabbi
Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak: תינוקת שלא הגיע זמנה לראות, Tinoket
shelo higia zmanah lirot, so here I actually say a baby, right,
a young girl that it's not her yet time to see, you
know, ten years old let's say, וראתה פעם ראשונה ושנייה, v'ra'asa pa'am
rishona u'shniya, okay,
she saw the first and second time. So we're back to the
biz.
It has not yet been three, three is from the same regular
24 hours back, one and two is still rare and a fluke
and not too concerned backwards.
So during that period, let's say we're not dealing with the stains,
which is what we dealt with before, but we're going to deal
with something else: רוקה ומדרסה, roka u'midrasah, her spit and places she
sat on. Okay, so if a woman is a נדה, niddah, so
not only is she טמאה, tamei, again this is not about her
status to her husband, it's about תרומה terumah and such issues, not
only is she טמאה tamei and if she touches things, but her
spit is considered to be an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, so you
know, as טמא tamei as she is, and same places she sits
on. What would be the status of those types of those things
בשוק? bashuk? You found them in the marketplace. Okay, so the question
is the same way and you don't know, she doesn't know, you
don't know when that's from. Okay, so somehow it's somehow, I don't
know how, somehow you know it was from this woman, there's this
place she sat on and place she spat, but she doesn't know
whether at that time she was a נדה niddah or not.
She was establishing what? A חזקה chazaka for two times being in
a ספיקא? s'feka? Or between two and three?
Right, presumably it's between two and three. That would make the question
more interesting. Okay, so it's between two and three and you don't
know whether it was during the time that she was טמאה tamei
or not during the time that she was טמאה. tamei.
רשות הרבים, Rishut harabim, so what's the question?
Well, ספיקא טהור, sefeika tahor, right? Right, that's partly it. תוספות Tosafot
also says that if it's בשוק bashuk as opposed to just in
terms of the practical issues, you know, there's more it's
there's more reason to sort of just have no idea when it
came from and just a be a of a much bigger doubt.
Okay.
But fundamentally רשות הרבים rishut harabim is enough to say that it's
ספיקא טהור. sefeika tahor. So what do you mean any this whole
אגדה? agada? Since זב zav when we say ספיקא טהור? sefeika tahor?
Yeah, but as we've seen, the גמרא Gemara is irregular, excuse
me, about when it applies the principle רשות הרבים rishut harabim משום
mishum ספיקא sefeika by a נדה. niddah. Okay, so anyway let's take
a look. So גמרא Gemara says, so בשוק טהור, bashuk tahor, I'm
sorry, כתמה נמי טהור. kitmah nami tahor. Okay, so because we'll be
lenient by the מדרס midras in the שוק, shuk, we'll be lenient
by the כתם. ketem. Now there's a big difference. The מדרס midras
in the שוק, shuk, the question is did she sit on this
thing or spit when she was a נדה niddah or not when
she was a נדה? niddah? Right? By the כתם, ketem, the question
is did it come from her or not come from her? So
you know, there's a
it's not exactly comparable, but anyway he makes the comparison. Okay, and
he says her כתם, ketem, but what's interesting for us is he
says the כתם ketem is טהור tahor even between two and three.
So ולא ידעינן אי דידיה אי דרביה. v'lo yad'inan i didei i
d'rabbai. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said in the name of רבי
שמעון בן יהוצדק, Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak, we don't know if it's
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan himself or whether he's just saying in the
name of his רבי. למאי נפקא מינה L'mai nafka mina what difference
does it make? למהוי דבר של אחד במקום שניים, L'mehavei dvar shel
echad b'makom shnayim, so whether it's going to be two against one.
Because before we had רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and חזקיה Chizkiya debating
whether the כתם ketem is טהור tahor between two and three. If
here it's not only רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan but also his רבי,
then it's רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and his רבי against חזקיה Chizkiya
and they win, two against one. But if it's if it's really
you know רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan himself, then it's not two against
one.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says, let me just check for
a moment...
Right. Okay.
So now the גמרא goes on. כי אתא רבין בכל נחותי ימא,
Ki ata Rabin b'chol nechetei yama, when רבין Rabin came from ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael and all those that went down to the sea,
whatever that means, some big group of people that went presumably from
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to בבל, Bavel, אמרוה כרבי שמעון בן יהוצדק.
amruha k'Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak. They said that this ruling that the
כתם ketem is טהור tahor between two and three, they said that
that was straight רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak and
it was not, you know, and therefore it was a third opinion
to the רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan himself, meaning actually I think I
misexplained it. Here clearly רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying in the
name of
רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק. Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak. But when רבי יוחנן...
Rabbi Yochanan or was he still reporting his רבי's authority? So here
and that would determine whether it's two opinions or three. So here
when they came back from Israel, they said that this position was,
okay fine. Anyway, they said that there was distinct positions. There was
a position of רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק Rabbi Shimon ben Yehosadak and
there was a position of רבי יוחנן and it was two against
one. And therefore we rule that the כתם kesem is
טהור. tahor. אמר רב חלקיא בר טובי, Amar Rav Hilkiya bar Tuvi,
so now we're onto a slightly different topic, but maybe we can
get to the two dots. אמר רב חלקיא בר טובי, Amar Rav
Hilkiya bar Tuvi, תינוקת שלא הגיע זמנה לראות, Tinokes shelo higia zemana
lereos, this young girl that has not yet regular, has not yet
started seeing, אפילו שופעת כל שבעה אין אלא ראייה אחת. Afilu shofas
kol shiva ein ela reia achas.
Let's say she bleeds for seven days straight. So remember, if she
bleeds three times, then you decide that now she is regular and
now she'll start she's considered to be 24 hours back and so
on. Let's say she bleeds over seven days. Is that one time
or three times?
Is she considered a זבה?
zava? No, because it was within seven days. Okay, more than seven
days you start worrying about זבה. zava. So he says that's once.
So that seems pretty obvious.
The גמרא says אפילו שופעת, afilu shofas, you mean even if she's
bleeding constantly? Talk about needing to go to a doctor.
ולא מבעיא פוסקת, Velo mibaia poseskes, it goes without saying if she
breaks. It's sounding like if she breaks it's obviously one ראייה. reia.
The opposite makes sense. If she's bleeding on and off, you're more
likely to count it as multiple. אדרבה, Adaraba, the opposite makes sense.
פוסקת הויא כשתי ראיות. Poseskes havya kishtei reiyos. If she breaks, it
should be like multiple seeings. She saw day one and day three
and day seven. Maybe that counts as seeing three times. אלא, okay
you're right. Here's what you should say. תינוקת שלא הגיע זמנה לראות
ושופעת כל שבעה אין אלא ראייה אחת. Tinokes shelo higia zemana lereos
veshofas kol shiva ein ela reia achas. If she's bleeding constantly, not
אפילו שופעת. afilu shofas. If, if she's bleeding constantly, that counts as
once. If she's bleeding one day and stops a day and another
day and stops a day and another day, even though it's all
within like a week, that's considered three separate times and therefore she's
now considered regular. Which is a little funny, obviously, because we all
know the, you know, biology is that it's all the same period.
It's not like it's proving more regularity even if it's starting and
stopping.
Should she be over eight days,
would she be a זבה? zava? זבה קטנה. Zava ketana. אמר רב
שימי בר חייא. Amar Rav Shimi bar Hiyya. מדלפת אינה כרואה. Medalefes
eina keroya. If a woman is just, if it's just coming out
not flowing, but not stop and start, but like dripping. You know,
a little bit, a little bit, it's continuous but it's a little
bit, it's not a flow. That's not like she saw. So what
do you mean, it's not like she saw? You mean she's טהורה?
tehora? והא קחזיא! Veha kachazya! She saw! She's obviously טמאה. temaya. אימא
אינה כשופעת. Eima eina keshofas. No, what I mean is, is that
it's not like the case of flowing. אלא כפוסקת. Ela keposeskes. It's
like stopping and starting. So here you have basically what would occur
every single time. A woman gets her period, woman, young girl, 10
years old, right, as long as it's not flowing, if it goes
over three days even if it's sort of like a little gradual
throughout, as long as it's not a flow, that's considered to be,
you know, with a little breaks, that's considered to be separate ראיות
reiyos and now she's considered regular.
The גמרא says: מכלל דשופעת כנהרא? Michlal deshofas kenehara? So what, the
one case where she's it's considered one ראייה reia is when she's
flowing like a river? So you know, the גמרא sort of recognizes
that that's absurd. What woman has that, you know, flows that degree?
And talked about, again, earlier talked about having to see a doctor.
אלא אימא, Ela eima, so no what I mean to say is,
he changes it again: אינה אלא כשופעת. eina ela keshofas. So yes,
if she's sort of, if it's sort of, you know, coming out
gradually and dripping and so on, that's what we mean by flowing.
We don't mean she has to flow like a river. So now
we're saying if a woman gets her period, woman, young girl, 10
years old, gets her period, it's over a few days, if it's
like constantly coming, flowing again, not flowing, you know, constantly dripping or
whatever, then it's considered one ראייה. reia. But if there's breaks, you
know, periods of not seeing and then starting again, that's multiple and
that makes her regular. Again, it's pretty funny.
She doesn't have to wait the 30 days?
She doesn't have to do the whole 30 days. It's very strange.
We would say in order to be regular, you need to wait
a minimum number of days to be considered like a new period.
So here the גמרא's being very formalistic, that with some break it's
already considered like another ראייה. reia.
How small can the breaks be?
Yes, it's not clear. I assume at least a day. I'm just
going to finish up to the two dots. תנו רבנן חזקה בנות
ישראל עד שלא הגיעו לפירקן הרי הן בחזקת טהרה ואין הנשים בודקות
אותן. Tanu Rabbanan chazaka bnos Yisrael ad shelo higiu lefirkun harei hen
bechezkas tahara ve'ein hanashim bodkos osan.
So before they girls have gotten to their, to puberty, they're considered
not to assume that they might bleed and nobody has to check
for them. And here's the other women, not pasking but helping them
see if they're bleeding. Women, nobody has to worry about them. We
assume they're not bleeding if they're prepubescent. משהגיעו לפירקן הרי הן בחזקת
טומאה. Mishehigiu lefirkun harei hen bechezkas tumah. Once they hit puberty, it
doesn't mean that they're טמאה, temaya, but it means we have to
be concerned they might be bleeding, right, because you know we've talked
about before, you bleed, you check twice a day, and you check
before this, and you check before that. There was so much checking
going on that as soon as a girl hits puberty, she has
to be worried that she might be getting her period.
ונשים בודקות אותן, Venashem bodkos osan, and other women will help check
her to see if she's gotten her period. So you know, talk
about being able to have that sort of privacy. all the time,
you know, instead of dealing with changes of your body, here as
soon as a woman, as a girl gets to that period, because
of the concern of touching טומאה tumah and touching תרומה terumah or
whatever, all these other women are getting involved, maybe it means her
mother, but whatever, helping her check to see if she's gotten her
period.
And then it's also the teacher.
It could be the teacher, right. רבי יהודה אומר אין בודקין אותה
ביד, Rabbi Yehuda omer ein bodkin osa beyad, they don't actually manually
check her מפני שמעוותות אותן mipnei shema'avtos osan
because that actually sort of can be damaging, which might mean it
might rupture the hymen, or it might mean that they can scratch
her inside and cause bleeding not based on the examination.
Right,
that's what I thought it meant.
Yeah, it's
maybe אלא, here's what you do, let's just finish this point. סכות
אותן בשמן, sachos osan beshemen, what they what they do is they
actually sort of give her a rubdown with
oil מבפנים mipenim and sort of
inside, okay, you know, ומקנחות אותן מבחוץ umakanchos osan mibachutz and wipes
outside. I'm not exactly sure what you're wiping if the oil was
on the inside, maybe the oil is outside and inside, so it's
a rubdown with oil and also goes inside, and then והן ניזוקות
מאליהן vehayn nizakos me'alehen and if they're ready to bleed somehow in
the process you'll see her bleeding and you do it without actually
doing a manual check. But there's still a manual, yeah, I don't
get it. Go and on that high. Another...